<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The whirl-wind of the Lord gone forth as a fiery flying roule, with an alarm sounded against the inhabitants of the north-countrey. Being a fore-warning to all the rulers in England, of the mighty and terrible day of the Lord, which shall overtake the wicked; but especially and in particular, to the persecuting rulers, priests, and people, in the county of Westmerland. Who by their fruits are made manifest to all, to be open enemies to Sions converts, and a generation of evil doers, with whom the Lord Jehovah is coming to plead the cause of the oppressed, and to redeem Zion with judgement, and her converts with righteousness. G.T.</title>
            <author>Taylor, Christopher, ca. 1615-1686.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95039</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T268</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T269</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E853_6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202135</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862533</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862533</idno>
            <idno type="VID">114696</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95039)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 114696)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 129:E853[6])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The whirl-wind of the Lord gone forth as a fiery flying roule, with an alarm sounded against the inhabitants of the north-countrey. Being a fore-warning to all the rulers in England, of the mighty and terrible day of the Lord, which shall overtake the wicked; but especially and in particular, to the persecuting rulers, priests, and people, in the county of Westmerland. Who by their fruits are made manifest to all, to be open enemies to Sions converts, and a generation of evil doers, with whom the Lord Jehovah is coming to plead the cause of the oppressed, and to redeem Zion with judgement, and her converts with righteousness. G.T.</title>
                  <author>Taylor, Christopher, ca. 1615-1686.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 17, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Giles Calvert, and are to be sold at his shop, at the Black-spread-Eagle neer the west end of Pauls, London,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>165[5]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>G.T. = Christopher Taylor, whose name appears on C1v.</note>
                  <note>The last digit of the publication date has failed to print. Some copies have this filled in with a "5" in MS.</note>
                  <note>Variant 1: pages 15, 16, and 17 are misnumbered 13, 12, and 9.</note>
                  <note>Variant 2: pages 16 and 17 are misnumbered 12 and 9. Page 15 is numbered correctly.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Sept. 12".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Quaker authors --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Westmorland (England) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:114696:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Whirl-wind of the Lord gone forth</hi> AS A Fiery flying Roule, <hi>WITH</hi> An Alarm ſounded againſt the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of the <hi>North-Countrey.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Being a Fore-warning to all the Rulers in <hi>England,</hi> of the mighty and terrible day of the Lord, which ſhall overtake the wicked; but eſpecially and in particular, to the perſecuting Rulers, Prieſts, and people, in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Westmerland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who by their fruits are made manifeſt to all, to be open ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to <hi>Sions</hi> Converts, and a Generation of evil doers, with whom the Lord <hi>Jehovah</hi> is coming to plead the cauſe of the oppreſſed, and to redeem <hi>Zion</hi> with judgement, and her Converts with righteouſneſs.</p>
            <q>For behold, the Lord will come with fire, and his Chariots like a whirl-wind, to vende<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his anger with fury, and his rebukes with flames of fire: for by fire, and by his Sword will the Lord plead with all fleſh, and the ſlain of the Lord ſhall be many, <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſa. 66.15.26.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>And I will puniſh the world for their evill, and the wicked for their Iniquity, and I will cauſe the arrogancy of the proud to ceaſe, and I will lay low the ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ght<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the terrible. <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſa. 13.11.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>He that hath an eare to hear let him hear, and he that hath an eye to ſee let him ſee; for that which is determined ſhall come to paſſe. <hi>And the Decree that is p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſhall ſurely be performed, And nothing of the Viſion ſhall fail, till all ſhall be fulfilled: he that can receive, let him.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>G. T.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop, at the <hi>Black-ſpread-Eagle</hi> neer the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls, London,</hi> 1655.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:114696:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:114696:2"/>
            <head>THE Whirl-wind of the Lord gone forth as a fiery flying Roule.</head>
            <p>TO all ye Rulers and Governours, Prieſt and people, who are turned from the light where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with Chriſt Jeſus hath enlightened you, and are found perſecuting thoſe who dwell in the light, who are moved of the Lord to declare againſt you, all who hate the light, whoſe deeds are evil, who dare not bring your deeds to the light, leaſt it ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove them: there is thy condemnation the light, the light which never changes: thou that liveſt in wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, turning to the light, it will reprove thee, thou who art proud turning to the light it will reprove thee; there thou haſt learned thy condemnation, the light, the light that is placed in thy heart, the eternal light, thou that turneſt from this light, art turned from God, and art a Child of darkneſs, and art in the broad way, and the condemnation of the Devil, thou hateſt the light, and dare not bring thy deeds to it, becauſe thou knowes they are evil, thou art a corrupt Tree, and bringeſt forth evil fruia and art to be cut down and caſt into the fire, thou cumbers the ground of the Lord, whoſe deeds are evil, thou art an unprofitable Servant, and hides the Lords Talent in the earth, thou devoures the Creatures of God, and ſpends them upon thy luſt, which the Lord hath created to be uſed in fear and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, to his prayſe and glory: therefore muſt thou give an account before the living God, who is Lord of Heaven and Earth, who made all things good, to be or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in his eternal wiſdom to his glory, which is
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:114696:3"/>received in the light, but thou who art turned from the light, art out of order, and ſpends the creatures upon thy luſt: the light leads to God the Father, from luſt, he that luſteth eateth, and is fallen under the condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; In that day thou eate, faith God, thou ſhalt die: ſo thou that haſt eaten, and art turned from the light, art in the death, and free from the life of God, and the light is thy condemnation, if thou turn into it, it will ſhew thee where thou art: thou drunkard turn into the light, that thou mayſt ſee thy ſelf, and come to repentances thou lyar and ſwearer, turn into the light, that it may reprove thee, thou ſlanderer and falſe accuſer, thou per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuter, railer and ſcorner, thou who liveſt in envy, who art in <hi>Cains</hi> way, who hates the light. Thou covetout oppreſſor, who grindes the faces of the poor, thou per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verter of juſtice, who art in the way of proud <hi>Haman.</hi> Tee outſide profeſſors, who have the form without the power of godlineſs: ye deceivers, who are in the ſteps of the falſe Prophets, which the true Prophets of the Lord cryed woe againſt, who ſeek for your gain from your quarter, greedy dumb dogs, which can never have enough, who teach for the wooll and fleece, and prepare warre againſt thoſe who put not into your mouths, who are greedy of filthy lucre, who are in the ſteps of the Scribes and Phariſees, Chriſt Jeſus cryed woe againſt, who hate the light, and with it are to be condemned from all the Children of the light, who love the light, and walk in the light, and to him there is no occaſion of ſtumbling; but he receives the light of life, the light is the condemnation of the world, which is ſet in mans heart, there the world is placed; who art turned from the light, thy heart is in the earth, and there is no room for God there; thou beareſt the earthly Image, which is ſin and death; for the life of God thou knowes nor, whoſe life is carnal, the pare Image thou beareſt not, where righteouſneſs dwells, where peace and joy is, where pure Religion is, where liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:114696:3"/>is, where is riches and pleaſures, where the mouth cannot come to corrupt, nor theeves break thorough and ſteal: this treaſure is hid in earthen veſſels; but the Lord will not dwell with a Cage of unclean birds, where the heart is not purified through the faith of Chriſt: the myſtery whereof, is held in a pure conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, where the unclean enters not, but is ſhut out with the light that comes from the Lord Jeſus: who are Children of the light live in righteouſneſs, and are the Servants of God, and have an everlaſting reward, who turn from the light of the Lord Jeſus, are turned from God, and from the faith of Chriſt, and from the pure Conſcience, whoſe conſciences are ſeared, and ſpeak lies in hypocriſie, and cry, Lord, Lord, and profeſs the name of God and Chriſt, whole hearts are full of rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenneſs, covetouſneſs, pride and oppreſſion, all which are condemned with the light, and all that profeſſion profeſſed in that nature, and all that ſacrifice is abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination to the Lord: the light ſearcheth and tryeth, bring all your works to the light, to try them whether they be wrought in God, for every one ſhall be rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded according to his works, whether they be good or evill. To the light in all conſciences I ſpeak, that with it you may ſee your ſelves and come to repentance, or elſe it will be your condemnation: this is the way to life, the light which never changes, this is the voice of Chriſt Jeſus, which calles for holineſſe and purity, from ſin and uncleanneſs, all that turn to the light, and love the light, they love God and Chriſt, from whence the light comes, and are led and guided by it, in the way of righteouſneſs, and from under the condemnation; but thou that hateſt the light, and walks contrary to the light, with the light art judged and condemned from all the Children of light, and thy practice and profeſſion is abomination to the Lord, though thou make a large profeſſion of the name of God and Chriſt, and the Saints words and practice, yet thou art without the life, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:114696:4"/>God in the world, out of the Croſſe of Chriſt Jeſus which crucifieth the fleſh with its affections and luſts, thou art covered with thy owne ſelf-righteouſneſſe, and art ignorant of the righteouſneſs of Chriſt Jeſus, and therefore thy work will burne and be conſumed in the day of the Lord God Almighty which is nigh at hand, in which day muſt every mans work be tryed, for the day will declare it, and God is pure and holy, and holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe becomes his houſe for ever, thou that liveſt in pride and pleaſures, and makes a profeſſion of God and godlineſſe, thy work will burne, thou that I veſt in luſt and uncleanneſſe and art covered with a profeſſion of godlineſſe, thy profeſſion is for the fire, there to be try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and conſumed, thou who art coveting after earthly things honours and dignities, and ſhroudeſt thy ſelfe under the figleaſe-garment of ſelf-righteouſneſſe and ſeeming godlineſſe, the Lord ſearcheth the heart, and tryeth the reines, and judgeth not as man judgeth, who knoweth all things: that is done in ſecret he ſeeth, and thou canſt not hide thy ſelfe from him, but he will ſearch thee and try thee, and ſee what is in thy heart, thou who haſt made a profeſſion of his Name, muſt come forth and confeſs to thy nakedneſſe before the living God, preiſt and people, profeſſor and prophane, now is the light ariſen to try you, and ſearch you: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore come to the light to be tryed and judged, whether thy works be wrought in God or no, yee high pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, and high preiſts, who are high in the Notion, come downe to the light, to try your works and life, thou who liveſt in thy luſt, and yet makeſt a profeſſion of puritie, thou art an hypocrite, and got above the Croſs of Chriſt Jeſus, who liveſt in the high conceits, in the proud uncrucified fleſhly minde, thou art ſuch as Chriſt Ieſus cryed woe againſt, who were large in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion as thou art, in the high Notion, got above the light, who ſaid and did not, and laid heavy burthens up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on others, and they themſelves would not touch them
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:114696:4"/>with one of their fingers, thou art a theeſe and a robber who climbeſt above the doore, which is Chriſt the light, into the profeſſion without the life. Chriſt is the way and reveales the Father of lights, who walk in the light walk not in darkneſs, who walk not in the light walk in darkneſſe, &amp; know not whither they goe, where ſchiſme, ſtrife and contention is, where the many waies is, loe here and loe there, as Chriſt foretold, but the light is but one and leads into unity and love, all that love it and walk in it, to the life which is but one, where all are of one heart and one mind, the pure mind, who obey the light which calls for puritie, this light leades out of the Fall up to God and Chriſt from whence it comes, all that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey it, out of the Fall through the Croſſe and death, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the beginning before the Fall, to the word of God, by which were all things made, and by which they ſtand, where the ſtedfaſtneſs and ſtanding is unmoveable up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Rock, where the power of death cannot enter, not the gates of hell cannot prevaile, which is over the world, and comprehends the world, with all its glories, where the eternall life is, where peace and reſt is, joy and gladneſs, rivers of pleaſures, and fulneſſe of joy for ever, Oh rejoyce yee Children of the light, who love the light, and walk in the light, ſhine forth as lights, in your words and works, in the mid'ſt of a crooked and deceitfull generation, the arme of the Lord is with you, which he is now ſtretching over the Nations, his right arme ſhall bring ſalvation, his power is over all and above all, which binds down all, that nothing can paſſe its limits and bounds, which are ſet by the unli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited power of God, before which power muſt all knees bow, and all tongues confeſſe, before which power muſt all ſtrong Oakes bow and tall Cedars, which po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer will blaſt and conſume in a moment, all the glory of this world, which power will daſh in peices the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly like a potters veſſel, which power ſhakes heaven
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:114696:5"/>and earth, and makes the ſtrong man bow himſelfe, which is derrible and dreadfull to the wicked, which power will be ſtretched out againſt the wicked in this day of his power, to deſtroy them, and hew them down by the arme of his power, his ſword is now drawne, and the power of the Lord begins to be terrible to the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, the ſound of the Almighty is gone forth, it is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry terrible, the ſound of his power is very dreadfull and terrible, the Trumpet is ſounding out of <hi>Sion,</hi> the great Alarum is allready begun, and the Inhabitants of the earth begin to feare and tremble, the ſinners in <hi>Sion</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to be afraid, and fearefullneſſe to ſurpriſe the hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite, the battell is begun, the great day of the Lord wherein he is ariſen in power to ſcatter the wicked and ungodly in their imaginations, and to throw downe the Kingdom of Antichriſt, his two edged ſword is drawne, it is fourbiſhed for a mighty ſlaughter and the bitter day of howling and lamentation is at hand, to come upon the wicked perſecutors, vaine profeſſors, ſwearers, drunkards, whoremongers, covetous perſons the high and lofty, and all the wicked of what ſort, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, or degree ſoever, the terrible day of the Lord is at hand, which will burn as an oven, and the proud, and the wicked muſt be caſt out into utter darkneſſe where will be bitter weeping and gnaſhing of teeth for ever; when all covers of vaine profeſſions will be too narrow to cover you with, from the ſight and preſence of God, and all your wickedneſſe will be laid open be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the true judge of heaven and earth, and every one muſt be rewarded according to his work: oh all yee po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers of the earth whoſe ſword ſhould be a terrour to the evil doers, and for the praiſe of them that doe well, heare the word of the Lord and feare before his power, which is now ariſen, which is the higher power, unto which our ſouls are ſubject, therefore in obedience to the command of God doe we declare againſt ſin, where in the light of God we ſee it, and are ſent of the living
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:114696:5"/>God to declare againſt it, openly in the gate without reſpect of perſons, for he that reſpecteth perſons com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth ſin, and is convinced by the law of God to be in the tranſgreſſion and out of the faith of Chriſt which is not had with reſpect of perſons: beware what ye doe, and how you lay your ſword upon the Children of the light, who love the light and walk in the light: beware how you account theſe offenders, who are ſent forth in the name and power of the Lord to declare againſt ſin and ſinners, and againſt all falſe worſhips, waye, and work; and to declare againſt the deceivers, Antichriſts and falſe teachers; and are ſent to call people to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and the feare of the living God, and to turne them from darkneſſe to the light; your ſword ſhould be for the praiſe of ſuch, and they ſhould have encouragement from you, in labouring in the work of the Lord, who abide in the doctrine of Chriſt, &amp; doe declare the day of the Lord which is at hand to overtake the wicked and ungod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, who by them are priſoned, ſtoned, and ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully entreated, upon ſuch you ought to lay your ſword, and not upon the righteous, therefore heare the word of the Lord oh ye perſecutors of the ſervants of the liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God, and here in the preſence of the living God I cleare my concience, and give you warning as I am commanded, that in the day of the Lord God, you may all be left without excuſe, and the Lord God may be cleare when he comes to judgment, and juſtified in his judgments: thus fait the Lord, woe unto the wicked, &amp; tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e who per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ecute my ſervants, whom I ſend out in my name, to declare my word &amp; meſſage to turn people fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> darknes to the light, that with the light they may ſee themſelves &amp; come to repentance; wo, wo, wo, unto you ſaith the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pirit of the living God better you had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver been borne, but that a Miſtone were hanged about your necks and you throwne into the Sea, the terrible power of God is ari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en his word is drawne to ew you downe, and give you your portion in the lake that ſhall
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:114696:6"/>never be quenched, then ſhall ye ſeeke repentance when it will be too late, and wiſh the Rocks and Hills might fall upon you, to cover you from the dreadful preſence of God, before the etenall fury and indignation of the living God: who is able to abide, who is everlaſting burnings and a conſuming fire: turne in to the light, and ſee where ye are, and how you ſtand in the ſight of God who will render his fury and indignation in flames of fire upon the wicked, then will it be a day of bitter howling to you, who fight againſt God and perſecute his ſervants, then muſt you bow under the mighty po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of the Lord, then your Crowne of pride will wither and be turned to duſt, and you will have no power nor ſtrength to help your ſelves, but you will be numbred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the ſlaine of the Lord, in this day of his power, wherein the Lord is ariſen, to plead with all fleſh by fire and ſword, and to get himſelf a name above every name, and to exalt his King, his ſonne Chriſt Jeſus, who is begun to reigne, and take the Kingdome which ſhall have no end, where righteouſneſs ſhall run downe the ſtreets as a river, who will rule the Nations with a rod of Iron, and daſh the heathen and all the proud perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of the righteous ſeed in pieces like a potters veſſel, and the ſervants of the Lord ſhall be glad and rejoyce and praiſe the Lord for ever, and ſhall have an everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reward, yea bleſſed are they that feare the Lord, and abide faithfull to the death, the Lord ſhall be unto them an everlaſting reward: oh rejoyce and be glad and lift up your heads you faithfull ones, you deare ſervants of the living God, lift up your heads and rejoyce and be valiant for the everlaſting truth, for truly friends and brethren, the preſent ſufferings are not to be reckoned to the glory that ſhal be revealed in us, as we abide faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: Oh deare freinds be encouraged, and quit your ſelves like men in the work of the Lord, the power of the Lord is with you, oh rejoyce, the Lord is your God, be faithfull and valiant, your reward is with you, who
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:114696:6"/>are faithfull, and you ſhall be Crowned with glory and honour for ever: let us rejoyce in the Lord, and be glad in the ſight of the heathen, who fret and vex becauſe the righteous ſeed will not bow to their pride, nor ſubmit to their wills, but chuſe rather to ſuffer affliction with the deare ſervants of the living God, then to enjoy the pleaſures of ſin for a ſeaſon. You who ſhould be Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of juſtice, and ſhould lay your ſword upon the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous, and not upon thoſe who dwell in the tender feare of God, I am moved of the Lord to give ſome of you warning in particular, and cleare my conſcience of you in the ſight of God, in love to your ſouls, that you may be left without excuſe, and that you and the reſt of the wicked and ungodly, and the perſecutors of what ſort ſoever, preiſt and people, all of you in generall, and you who are after named in particular within this County of <hi>Weſtmorland,</hi> that you are warned from the word of the living God, and that you may remember that you have beene often warned in your life time, and here in the ſight of God, I cleare my conſcience of you all in giving you once more warning and every of you within this County of <hi>Weſtmorland,</hi> you who are called Juſtices or gentlemen, high and low, and all you preiſts and blind guides, to you I declare it in the preſence of the living God, as I am commanded of him, that you are mutherers of ſoules, and all the blood of ſarted ſoules under your dead miniſterie, will be required at your hands: and to you people I cleare my concience, in the ſight of God, you are now warned, I doe declare it to you all in the preſence of the Lord that the light wherewith Chriſt Ieſus hath enlightened you, which if you turne in to it, there is your onely true teacher, and way to life, and will be your condemnation going on to diſobey it, and here I am in the ſight of God cleare of a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> your blood, in giving you all and every of you from the higheſt to the loweſt warning, that you repent and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to the Lord ſpeedily, leaſt the Lord haſten his
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:114696:7"/>judgments upon you, herein I am cleare of your blood if ye periſh your blood be upon your own heads for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver: <hi>Thomas Burton</hi> of <hi>Branton</hi> in <hi>VVeſtmorland</hi> neare <hi>Appleby,</hi> called Juſtice, by whom I was committed to priſon, and here have remained under cruell ſufferings and inhumane uſage above one whole yeare impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for ſpeaking the word of the Lord to thy preiſt in the ſteeple houſe yard, as I was commanded of the liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God, which was the breach of no known law of this Nation. Thou bloody perſecutor of the ſervants of the living God, who didſt likewiſe commit to priſon the deare ſervants of the living God, who are deare and faithfull witneſſes to the eternall truth of God, againſt al the ſerpents brood, in whoſe mouth is no guile found: oh woe unto thee, better thy mothers wombe had beene thy grave, except thou ſpeedily repent, turne in thy mind to the light to ſee thy pride, and haughtineſſe of thy heart; with It ſee thy ſelfe and repent, leaſt the heavy and feareful judgments of God fall upon thee, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which thou canſt not ſtand, but muſt be broken in peices. I doe here in the pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ence of the living God cleare my conſcience, and give you the laſt warning, all of you who have had a hand in perſecuting the ſervants of the Lord, within this County of <hi>Weſtmoreland,</hi> and I give ſome of you warning in particular, <hi>John Archer,</hi> called Juſtice; <hi>James Cooke,</hi> late Major of <hi>Kendall, Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Neviſon</hi> of <hi>Nuby-ſtones; Thomas Gabetis</hi> called Sheriffe; <hi>Francis Higginſon,</hi> prieſt of <hi>Kirbyſtaven,</hi> who did ſay there was not an eternall light in thee, and that there was nothing eternall in man, thou haſt manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thy ſelf to be a carnall bruite; who haſt denyed the Lord that bought thee, and art a Reprobate out of thy own mouth, and ſaid Chriſt was in heaven with a car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall body: thou ſhameleſſe Preiſt, who muſt needs be a bloody perſecutor, who knowes nothing of God in thee but numbreſt thy ſelf amongſt the bruite beaſts that pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, and thou Preiſt <hi>Rowlands</hi> who art one with <hi>Hig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginſon,</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:114696:7"/>in thy blaſphemie, and ſaid the ſoule of man was not now eternall; thou carnall bruite, what doe yee blind Preiſts preach to, if the ſoule of man be not eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, and if there be nothing eternall in man, and if e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man be not enlightened with an eternall light, here in the preſence of God I give you warning aforenam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and all the reſt of the perſecutors, who have ſtrengthened the hands of the wicked againſt the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, prieſt and people: you prieſts have been often warned from the word of the Lord, and your deceitfull practices laid open, and the people have been called from that falſe worſhip, that you lead them in, to that worſhip which is in ſpirit and truth, to the true and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting teacher, therefore are ye all left without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe, in giving you all warning, within this County of <hi>Weſtmoreland,</hi> both prieſt and people, high and low, and thou Towne of <hi>Applebie,</hi> here in the preſence of the Lord<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I cleare my conſcience of thee, and doe give thee warning that thou repent and returne to the feare of the Lord ſpeedily, or elſe expect thoſe woes and judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to come upon you, which have been denounced from the word of the Lord by his ſervants, for not one title muſt fall to the ground: woe woe woe unto thee <hi>Applebie,</hi> how often haſt thou beene warned and called to repentance, and there is not one in thee, of thine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants, that feare the Lord, therefore doe I in the ſight of God, clear my conſcience of thee, and do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare unto thee, that the ſad and heavy judgements of God are to come upon thee, which thou ſhalt not eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape; for it is the word of the Lord to thee: you bloody perſecuters, you raylers, ſwearers, curſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>peakers lyars and ſlanderers, you muſt all periſh in the lake toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, except ye ſpeedily repent: ye Drunkards, Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers and Adulterers, blaſphemers, you filthy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean perſons, who lie wallowing in your filthy lives, as the Sow lies wallowing in the mire and dirt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo little of the fear of God there is among you: you people of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:114696:8"/>
               <hi>Appleby,</hi> here in the preſence of the living God, I clear my conſcience of thee, and give thee thy laſt warning from the Lord by me, that when the ſad, lamentable, and heavy judgements of God come upon you, you may remember, you had warning from the word of the Lord, by one of his Servants. Oh all ye people, who have heard the ſound of the truth throughout this whole Nation, I am moved of the living God to give you all warning, the Lord is getting himſelf a name in this Nation, and raiſing up the Kingdom of his beloved Son Chriſt Jeſus, he is ſending forth his Meſſengers and Servants in his name and power, to call all to the light, which is the teaching of the Lord, from all other falſe wayes and worſhips, wherein they have been led, where their ſouls have not been profited, where the many con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed cries have been, as loe here, and loe there, to you all I am moved to write, that you may all be warned, as I am moved of the living God, whatſoever your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion be, that you come out of your dead forms to the light of Chriſt Jeſus, wherewith you are enlightened, that with it you may ſee your ſelves, and the deceitful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of your hearts and wayes, that you come to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and the fear of the Lord, and learn of Chriſt who was meek and lowly in heart, to pull down your pride and ſtrong conceits, and high thoughts, and vain imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, and turn to the living God, that he may be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured by you, and his judgements may be removed from you, who reject the Counſel of God, and contend quarrel and diſpute againſt the everlaſting truth, upon which they will in the end ſplit themſelves, and be broken in peeces: here I declare it unto you, in the preſence of the living God; and he that can receive it let him: here is your way to life, the light, the light which changes not, the light in every ones conſciences, which checks for ſin, and calls to repentance, loving this light: here is your teacher, and obeying of it, it will lead you up to God, into eternal reſt, peace and ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:114696:8"/>from ſin and ungodlineſs, hating this light, and blaſpheming it, calling it natural, and acting contrary to it: here is your condemnation, the light, take war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and repent betimes, oh all people every where; for it is hard for you to kick againſt the pricks; for the mighty God is ariſen in power, not only to ſhake the earth, but the Heavens alſo, and to create new Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, and a new earth, wherein dwells righteouſneſs; and to overturn the Kingdom of Antichriſt, root and branch, with its foundation and ſtrength, that all may come to build upon the everlaſting foundation which is already laid, Chriſt the light, to witneſs the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God in Chriſt Jeſus, thorough the death of ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs, all high conceits, and angry notions, that God Almighty may be honoured, and all may bow to the Scepter of his Son, and throw down their glories at his feet, that he alone may be honoured and worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and all proud fleſh abaſed in his ſight, according to the word of the Lord, that he that glories, may glory in the Lord. Oh all people within this County of <hi>Westmerland,</hi> and throughout the whole Nation: this is the word of the Lord God A mighty to you, that you may be all warned, Prieſt and People, you that are in forms, or got above forms, or live in the form of truth only, without the life and power; and here is your only true teacher the light, the light which ſhines into your Conſciences, and if you turn into it, and minde it, it will open your underſtandings, and let you ſeeplainly where you are, whether you be in the broad way, or the narrow way, the light will ſearch you, and try you, and rip up your hearts, and will ſhew you all your thoughts, and every idle word, for which you muſt give an account before the Lord, and if you obey it, it will be your ſalvation, and if you diſobey it, it will be your condemnation: the light, the light wherewith ye are enlightned, which comes from Chriſt Jeſus, which is the grace of God,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:114696:9"/>which hath appeared to all men, the free teacher of righteouſneſs, the everlaſting light, which never chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, in which as you turn into it, it will ſhew you what is the will of God and ſhew all ſin and wickedneſſe, and all deceit, and call you from it; and if you obey it, it will lead you into truth, and from all falſe worſhips, to the true worſhip of God, which is in ſpirit and truth, where all deceit and hypocriſie, will with the light be judged and condemned; and abiding in it, it will teach you the true knowledge of God, and of his will, and in the light you will come to comprehend the world, and the deceits and vanities that are in it, pride and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, formality and hypocri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e; and oh all people know this, that if any fall from the light, as <hi>Judas,</hi> who betrayed innocent blood, and had recei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed part of the Miniſtry, and do crucifie Gods Sonne afreſh, and put him to open ſhame, by which the great offence comes, and the way of truth comes to be evil ſpoken of, all ſuch with the light are condemned and judged, who are departed from it, into the luſt and filth; ſuch we deny, and do teſtifie againſt openly, in the pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ence of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God: yea better they had never been born, who were once enlightned, and had taſted of the good word of God, and are fallen from the holy Commandement, into the way of perdition: offences will come, but woe unto them by whom they come, herein is the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture fulfilled, and the falling away, that thoſe that are approved may be made manifeſt, and the ſteadfaſtneſs of all proved and tryed: and this is no new thing, but was ordained of old, that all may be tryed and proved, and bleſſed are all they that abide faithful, grounded upon the Rock, unmoveable; they ſhall have an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting reward, when <hi>Demas</hi> and <hi>Judas</hi> muſt go down into perdition, and all that turn from the light, from following the Lamb, who are not willing to part with all for Chriſt, who is the everlaſting treaſure, which the world knowes not, nor can learn by the Serpents wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:114696:9"/>which is accurſed from God, and all the Serpents brood, who are in the many inventions, making Images and forms of truth, and likeneſſes of pure Religion and righteouſneſs; but the life they know not, which is eternal, and immortal; beware of dogs, beware of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion; ſeparate your ſelves from unrighteouſneſſe without, and learn Chriſt, who is within the vail, through the death ariſen and aſcended far above all principalities and powers, and hath led captivity cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, and hath through death overcome him, who had the power of death, that is, the Devil, and is ſet down at the right hand of God, for ever, making interceſſion by his blood, whoſe righteouſneſs is pure, and all are Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins that follow the Lamb, cloathed in white linnen, who are redeemed to the Lamb through his blood, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in the greatneſſe of his ſtrength trodden the Wine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe of the wrath of God and there was none to help him, without the Camp of God, where all the perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of the righteous ſeed muſt be trodden in pieces, and drink of the Cup of the Lords fury and indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which is to be given them without mixture, and they muſt drink it, and be drunk and mad, as it is at this day: he that can receive it let him; and be warned O all people and repent, now while it is called to day, leaſt the word of the Lord be fulfilled upon you, he that hath an ear to hear let him hear: here is your teacher the light, and will lead you to God, and bring ſalvation, if you love it and obey it; and your condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, if you diſobey it: and here I have cleared my Conſcience, in the ſight of God, as I was commanded, in ſhewing thee the way to life, that you may be all left without excuſe, and God may be clear, Oh <hi>England,</hi> of thy blood, and all his faithful Servants, who have faithfully given thee warning, thy blood be upon thy own head if thou periſh; and he that commeth out of thy ſins, doth deliver his ſoul, and come to eternal life; to the light of Chriſt in every one of your Conſciences. I ſpeak which ſhall be my witneſs, and your condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:114696:10"/>that hate it, from him who to all your ſouls, is a friend, who is at the giving forth of this, a priſoner in the common Goal at <hi>Appleby</hi> in <hi>Westmerland,</hi> for the truths ſake, known to the world by the name of <hi>Christopher Taylor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let this be ſcattered throughout the Nation, that</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>may have warning, that the living God may be clear when he judgeth, and all his Servants may be clear of his blood, who is about to raiſe up his Name, and ſpread his truth throughout the Nations, and gather in the diſperſed amongſt them, that the Word of the Lord may be fulfilled, and the Kingdoms of this world may become the Kingdom of Chriſt, that there may be one Shepherd, and one fold, to the glory and prayſe of his Name, who is Lord of Lords, and King of Kings, God bleſſed for ever, who will reign in power and glory, to the astoniſhment of all the Heathen, who muſt be broken in pieces, and ſubjected under the mighty power of God, and the Lord will reign in power, who is coming with ten thouſand of his Saints to judge the world. Oh the glory of God, the glorious reign of</hi> Sions <hi>King, whoſe Scepter is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting, and a Scepter of righteouſneſs, which ſhall have no end, bleſſed and prayſed be the Lord, and bleſſed are his ſervants, who behold his glory and power, which is a terror to the Nations: the ſhout of a King is amongst you, clap your hands for joy, our God liveth and reigneth, and is on our ſide, and we need not fear what man can do unto us, as we abide faithful to him: the ſhout of a King is with us, glory to the Lord for ever, ride and proſper in the name of the Lord you need no other Weapon, it is the Lords work, ride on in power: the power of the Lord of Hoaſts is with you,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:114696:10"/>to the pulling down of ſtrong holds, and wake you a terrour to your enemies: your Weapons are not carnal, but mighty through God, the bleſſing of the eternal God is with you: your honour is to binde Kings in Chains, and Nobles in Fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Iron, whoſe Crown is not mortal, but a Crown of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall glory: this is the portion, and the Heritage of all his Saints, and thoſe that fear the living God, who take warning and repent, who love the light and walk in it, to receive the light of life, where the bleſſedneſs is with God bleſſed for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>30. day, 5. <hi>m.</hi> (55).</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
